if you're looking for a new solid
barbell to add to your home gym well
you're most likely going to want to go
after a multi-purpose bar since you can
switch between bench pressing to power
cleaning in a matter of seconds again
faster since it's their evolution
barbell so today I'm going to break down
all my findings for you guys
[Music]
what's up everybody it's Jake back once
again in the barbin garage gym with yet
another barbell review we're ready to go
for y'all this time I have the again
faster Evolution barbell I'm pretty
pumped to take you through everything
this bar has to offer from the price and
the features some pros and cons that you
might experience as well as who should
or maybe should not buy this barbell
okay but before I get started you know I
have to let you know we've reviewed a
lot of barbells on barbin.com and if you
want to browse our best list just go and
search bar Bend best barbells and you
can find out for yourself which one
cracks that number one spot
okay so what do I like about this
barbell well y'all know me I'm all about
the green and in terms of pricing the
evolution bar is a solid option it's
listed right around 200 on the again
faster website and in my opinion I think
you're are going to be really hard
pressed to find a better deal than this
one is especially considering the
tensile strength rating which is right
at 190 000 PSI that's really respectable
but if you don't know what that means
essentially it's going to tell you how
strong a bar is and how much punishment
that it can handle so this typically
ranges from 120 000 PSI to 230 maybe
even 235 000 PSI so once again this is
really respectable
the moderate knurling paired with the
bronze bushings in the loading sleeves
is going to make this a really solid
option for any of those Olympic lifters
even crossfitters out there for you to
purchase and since it's also available
in 15 kilograms as well as this 20
kilogram version that I have right here
there's a lot of people that can get
some solid usage out of this barbell
the evolution does not Feature A Center
knurling overall knurling is pretty much
on the moderate side and it does utilize
bronze bushings to provide a spin in the
loading sleeves so any Olympic lifters
or even those crossfitters out there
this is a really good option for you to
consider this bar also is available in
15 kilograms so there really is an
option for everyone
[Music]
okay so let's talk about some issues
that you might experience with the
evolution let's talk about the coating
first and foremost it is coated in
Chrome now in terms of protection
against rust and corrosion
it's not going to be the ideal solution
for everybody especially if you're like
myself and you are working out in a
garage and it tends to get pretty humid
you know you're gonna have to clean this
barbell pretty frequently but you know
if you're in a climate controlled place
and you're working out in your home you
might be just fine it's just it's worth
mentioning that you don't have a center
knurling right here I personally like
that but I understand why some people
might not enjoy that because you
definitely lose out on a little bit of
grip on your chest during a power clean
and especially as you're going to do
some back squats so keep that in mind
the overall knurling it's pretty
moderate it's pretty passive in your
hands it's not going to cut too deep
which might be great for some people but
you know if you already have rough hands
calluses built up or maybe you just
really like an abrasive grip that's not
the case right here and you know the
loading sleeves while they technically
have a bit of a pattern if you run your
hand across it you can feel it they're
pretty smooth so I always recommend
using weight collars but you're
absolutely going to need some if you go
to do some power cleaning so really any
lift or the bar tends to drop onto the
ground so your plates don't slide off
[Music]
okay so in terms of pricing the
evolution bar is listed right at 200
bucks that's a pretty sweet deal to me
you're going to be able to fully build
out your home gym without absolutely
Breaking the Bank you know there's some
barbells out there that have the exact
same pencil strength rating but they're
nearly two hundred dollars more now some
of those might be stainless steel but
that's still you know twice the amount
you're spending on this barbell and you
know since you are getting a set of
relatively low price you know you can
add more to your home gym you can go get
that new power rack you want maybe some
sweet bumper plates some kettlebells
really whatever it is you can do that
with this barbell which is a really nice
selling point in my opinion
[Music]
okay so let's talk about the build now
with the evolution we have the 20
kilogram version right here it's 86
inches in length with 16 and a half inch
loading sleeves and a diameter of 28
millimeters it's also available in 15
kilograms times that one's going to be
79 inches in length with 12 and a half
inch loading sleeves and that one's
going to feature diameter of 25
millimeters once again it's not
available in 10 kilograms so if it's
something you're looking for you have to
look elsewhere okay so this is crafted
with alloy steel and it's coated in
Chrome it looks really good
but it's not going to be the ideal
solution in terms of rust and corrosion
you know I've had mine for a little bit
now and I'm already getting signs of
that so I just need to clean it that's
bad on me but this is something you're
going to have to clean every so often
but you know since it's available at a
low price tag I think it's worth
cleaning it a couple times a month
the tensile strength is 190 000 PSI
that's pretty solid I think that's going
to be able to handle the punishment from
the majority of the weightlifting
community so that's really nice in
itself and you know the knurling right
here
kind of passive to be completely honest
you know knurling's not really a one
size fits-all feature in my opinion so
some of you really might enjoy this
right here but for me you know my hands
tend to sweat I've told you all that
before and you know this just doesn't
really provide me with the most optimal
grip during my lifts the bronze bushings
in the loading sleeves do provide a nice
spin right here they don't spin as
freely as some other barbells I've
reviewed and even used but you know it's
still there it's still going to give you
that spin you need to rep out some power
cleans but since they don't spin out of
control that's going to be really nice
for your power lifting movements for a
bench press for example you don't have
to worry about the sleeve starting to
rotate on you because that's pretty
uncomfortable and can just kind of mess
with your lift in general
foreign
[Music]
let's talk about the knurling again you
know as I said it's not very abrasive
that's might not be ideal for a lot of
you power lifters but it's going to be
great for high rep exercises it's not
going to tear up your hands as that bar
is kind of rotating in your hands so
that's a nice touch you do not have the
choice of a center knurling on this
barbell you can feel either way about it
I personally like not having it but I
understand why some people would prefer
having it you do have dual neural
markings right here that's going to be
really nice as you go to get set up for
a power lift these on the inside and you
know your Olympic and Crossfit style
lifts that's what this outer one is
going to be that's set by the
international weightlifting Federation
the one on the inside that's set by the
international power lifting Federation
now you do have bronze bushings in both
of the sleeves that's going to provide a
spin they don't spin out of control you
know I have used some other ones that
spin faster than this that's going to be
pretty nice four power lifts as I
mentioned just a second ago this can be
really nice for you Ron's bushings are
found in a lot of multi-purpose bars
such as this one right here they're cost
effective and you know they do provide a
pretty nice rate of spin the loading
sleeves technically have a pattern if
you run your fingers across it you can
feel some grooves but at the same time
it's pretty smooth you don't really want
your plates doing the Electric Slide
while you're lifting so you're
definitely going to want to throw some
weight collars on there just to help you
out and one really cool thing with this
barbell is that it does feature a
lifetime warranty now
that's not going to cover you know where
normal wear and tear and definitely not
any negligent use but it is going to
cover any manufacturing defects so
that's pretty nice too
[Music]
all right guys let's do a quick walk
around with the evolution bar you know
once again this is coated in Chrome as
you can see you don't have a center
knurling right here I like that I
understand if you don't like that
because you do lose out on some
grippiness for different exercises but
you don't have that option here so the
overall knurling is pretty passive you
know to me I don't think knurling is a
one size fits all feature like I said so
some of you might like that and honestly
it's great for some high rep exercises
but maybe not for a super heavy deadlift
you do have dual neural markings right
here so this one on the inside that is
set by the international powerlifting
Federation and you guessed it on the
outside is set by the international
weightlifting Federation so you can
definitely get identical hand placement
on the barbell you have to worry about
one hand being further out than the
other
as we come down the line you will see
the bronze bushings right here it's
going to provide that spin you know
obviously it does spin but not as freely
as some other ones do and look if you
look right up close you will see some
signs of corrosion rust already I
haven't had this barbell very long so
you know I'm already seeing signs of
that it's partly on me you know I
haven't cleaned this as frequently as I
should but you know this is something
you're absolutely going to have to do
with this barbell and if you look up
close you know you can definitely see
there is a little bit of a Groove
pattern right here especially if you run
your fingers across you can feel it but
you know it's not cut very deep now if I
were to throw a plate on here you can
absolutely hear it
but you know since they aren't cut very
deep you're definitely going to need
some weight collars I always suggest
using one anyways but especially with
this bar because if you don't you're
gonna have some sliding of your plates
so just snap that bad boy on there and
you really should be good to go
[Music]
okay so who should purchase the again
faster Evolution barbell well this is
going to be a really solid bar for
beginners to grow with you know it's not
going to tear up your hands if you don't
have any calluses plus you can grow with
it since it does have a tensile strength
rating of 190 000 PSI plus if you're
wanting to save some money and fully
build out your home gym you know this is
listed at 200 that's going to be a
really solid option for you since it
does not have a center knurling overall
knurling's pretty moderate and it does
have bronze bushings in the sleeves I
think Olympic lifters and crossfitters
are going to get some solid usage out of
this barbell and if you don't want a 20
kilogram bar you know this is available
in 15 kilograms so that would be a
really good option for you also
[Music]
okay so what about the people who might
not want to purchase the evolution
barbell well for starters if you do in
fact need a barbell to have a higher
tinsel strength rating than 190 000 PSI
and you probably want to keep looking
because that's where this one caps out
also you know if you're really focusing
on power lifts this might not be the bar
for you mainly because of the knurling
so people who you know have a high
emphasis in power lifting well they're
most likely going to want to barbell
it's really abrasive and since you know
this one is not might not be the ideal
solution for you and lastly you know
it's the coding you know it's coated in
Chrome so if you are in fact you know
working out all your equipment is stored
in a garage maybe you don't have AC in
there you're going to experience some
Rust and corrosion on here so you're
gonna have to clean it a few times once
a month and if that's something you
really just don't want to do that often
I'd suggest going after a stainless
steel bar but you're still gonna have to
clean that one too
[Music]
all right y'all that's all I have for
you today on the again faster Evolution
barbell this is a really solid option
for any beginner to consider because you
know you're going to be able to grow at
this bar you're going to be saving money
without sacrificing utility this is just
as versatile really as any other
multi-purpose bar out there and the
tensile strength is very respectable but
you know remember the knurling is not
very abrasive so you might need some
assistance in terms of getting that grip
that you're looking for and since it's
coated in Chrome you're gonna have to
clean it more frequently than you would
with some other Coatings out there
thanks for watching everybody I hope
this video was really helpful that I was
able to answer some questions that you
might have about this bar as always stay
posted for my next review but for now
head over to barbin.com and you can read
more about this barbell just search bar
Bend again faster Evolution barbell
review and you can read over everything
I discussed here today I'll see you on
next song
[Music]